Mohammed Talib

Email: talibilat2019@gmail.com | Mobile: +447776696459

<u>LinkedIn</u> | <u>GitHub</u> | <u>Medium</u>

SUMMARY

Al Engineer with a Master's in Al, specialising in **RAG chatbots**, **MLOps**, **Azure** and **workflow automation**. Currently at Factor, working as Sr Al Engineer in **Al R&D** and **optimising RAG** chatbot responses using **Multi-Agent Architecture**. Experienced in **data preprocessing**, **predictive modeling**, and **data visualisation**.

Active content creator with over **100 blogs** published and invited as a **guest speaker** at AI/LLM talks and University of Essex. Recognised as a **LinkedIn AI Top Voice** and **mentored** 10+ on ADP List, guiding individuals into AI roles.

WORK EXPERIENCE

Factor Law

December 2024 - Present

Sr Al Engineer

Belfast, Northern Ireland, United Kingdom | Hybrid

- Building end-to-end accelerators for lawyers and reduced crafting, analysing and negotiating 1000s of contract by 95%.
- Mentoring a team of AI engineers, fostering their technical growth and career development.
- Aiding in the definition and execution of the technical strategy for AI R&D initiatives.
- Building and maintaining relationships with key stakeholders, including senior leadership and clients.

TheTin

October 2023 - November 2024

AI and LLM Technologist

London, England, United Kingdom | Hybrid

- Developed a prototype for C-Suite executives using OpenAI GPT-4 and LangChain, leveraging multi-agent architecture.
 - * Compared the performance and cost of open-source models like **Llama** and **Mistral** with commercial models such as **OpenAI** and **Claude.**
 - * Delivered a solution allowing executives to consume summarised thought pieces in real-time, tailored to their roles and industries.
- Created a RAG chatbot for professional services integrated within Microsoft Teams, utilising Power Virtual
 Agents and Azure Bot Services.
 - * Utilised **Microsoft Document Intelligence** for data structuring and **Azure AI Search** for chunking, indexing, and querying thousands of PDFs.
 - * Deployed the chatbot via **Azure Web App**, which provided real-time project updates, improving communication and decision-making workflows.

Data Glacier

April 2023 - September 2024

Remote – Colchester

Natual Language Processing Intern

- Conducted sentiment analysis using NLP techniques to analyse customer feedback and social media data, extracting valuable insights with 87% accuracy
- **Developed NLP modeling** tools to classify resumes, leveraging **transformer-based models** like **BERT** implemented on the **PyTorch** architecture, achieving 95% accuracy in resume analysis through **transfer learning**.
- **Deployed** predictive models using **APIs**, integrating them into production systems and ensuring seamless performance through platforms like **Postman** for testing and validation.

EDUCATION

University of Essex

Colchester, United Kingom

Masters of Science in Artificial Intelligence (Grade: 1st Class)

Jan 2022 - Jan 2023

SKILLS

Languages : Python, SQL, JavaScript

Frameworks : TensorFlow, Keras, pyTorch, Flask, LLMFlow, LangChain, FastAPI, React **Libraries** : Pandas, NumPy, SciPy, Matplotlib, Scikit-learn, NLTK, OpenCV, Tkinter

DataBase: PostgreSQL, Alembic, Pydantic, SQLAlchemyDev Tools: Visual Studio Code, Git, Pinecone, Docker, PowerBIOthers: Agile, Data Pipeline, Azure Al Services, CI/CD, OAuth2

Local Retrieval-Augmented Generation (RAG)

PyTorch, Python, React, HuggingFace, FastAPI

Source Code

- Developed a local **RAG** system without using LangChain or other framework, used PyTorch for storing embeddings and **OpenAI's function calling** to mitigate hallucination.
- Implemented a backend using **FastAPI**, providing an efficient API for document search and retrieval, while ensuring low latency in question-answering tasks.
- · Used React for frontend

Social media using FastAPI

FastAPI, PostgreSQL, Pydantic, Alembic, Docker, Github Actions, Ubuntu

Source Code

- Built a **scalable** social media platform using **FastAPI**, implementing features like account creation, authentication (**OAuth2**), and **CRUD** operations for posts.
- Integrated functionality for users to like/dislike posts and track the count of interactions in real-time.
- Deployed the application using **Docker** and managed database migrations with **Alembic**.
- Created a CI/CD pipeline using GitHub Actions and deployed it on Digital Ocean(Ubuntu).

Al-powered Voice and Video Chatbot for Website Navigation

Python, Langchain, Azure, WebRTC

Source Code

- It is an ongoing side project in which I design and implement a chatbot that clones the user's face and voice to assist with website navigation. The chatbot provides real-time responses and interactions through text, voice, and video.
- Built the backend for crawling and chunking web data, which is indexed and processed using a language model to
 provide contextual responses. The chatbot also uses an Al avatar for video responses and a webview for real-time
 website interaction.
- The system supports multiple modes of communication, including **text**, **voice**, and **video**, while ensuring smooth user experience and accurate website navigation.

LARGE LANGUAGE MODELS

Python, TensorFlow, pyTorch, Google Colab

Source Code

- Developed expertise in prompt engineering, local training of Large Language Models (LLMs) using self-annotated data, and transfer learning.
- Explored the relationship between **Named Entity Recognition (NER)** and **Google BERT** by training the last layer of the model and employing different architectures to improve accuracy.

HUMAN ACTIVITY RECOGNITION USING SMART-WATCH

TensorFlow, SQL, Android

Source Code

- Built a mobile app on an **energy-efficient IoT** platform that utilized smartphones and wearable devices to track and monitor 11 activities, employing **TensorFlow Lite** for training and inference.
- Prioritized user data security and privacy through Federated Learning and implemented a communication interface
 with Message Queue and MQTT protocol, yielding 95% results with Convolution and LSTM layers.

CERTIFICATIONS AND ACHIEVEMENTS

- Guest Speaker at a Futures Forum: AI/LLM event.
- Invited to host Director's workshop for Essex Business School students on AI
- Got Featured on DZone Home Page
- 30k+ Medium Blog Views on 100+ blogs with 250+ followers
- Al Top Voice on LinkedIn
- Microsoft Azure Fundamental
- Mentored 10+ people to transition their career into Al.